<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second part of the enquiry into the reasons offered by Sa. Oxon for  abrogating the test: or an answer to his plea for transubstantiation; and for acquitting the Church of Rome of idolatry</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77908</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5870B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231153</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899772</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133214</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77908)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133214)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2441:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second part of the enquiry into the reasons offered by Sa. Oxon for  abrogating the test: or an answer to his plea for transubstantiation; and for acquitting the Church of Rome of idolatry</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing CD-ROM, 1996.</note>
                  <note>By Gilbert Burnet.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Customs and practices --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Transubstantiation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133214:1"/>
            <head>A Second part of the ENQUIRY Into the REASONS Offered by <hi>Sa. Oxon</hi> for abrogating the TEST: Or an ANSWER to his Plea for <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and for Acquitting the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> of IDOLATRY.</head>
            <p>THe two ſeemingly contrary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the <hi>Wiſeman,</hi> of <hi>Anſwering a Fool according to his Folly,</hi> and of <hi>not Anſwering him according to his Folly,</hi> are founded on ſuch Excellent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that if a man can but rightly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish the Circumſtances, he has a good Warrant for uſing both upon different oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. The Reaſon for <hi>Anſwering a Fool according to his Folly,</hi> is, <hi>leſt he be wiſe in his own eyes;</hi> that ſo a haughty and petulent humour may be ſubdued; and that a man that is both blinded and ſwelled up with ſelf-conceit, may by ſo ſevere a Remedy be brought to know himſelf, and to think as meanly of himſelf as every Body elſe does. But the reaſon againſt <hi>Anſwering a Fool ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Folly,</hi> is, <hi>leſt one be alſo like unto him,</hi> and ſo let both his mind and ſtile be corrupted by ſo Vicious a Pattern. Since then in a former <hi>Paper,</hi> I was wrought on to let our Author ſee, what a ſevere Treatment he has juſtly drawn on him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to write in a ſtile a little like his own, I will now let him ſee, that he is the man in the World, whom I deſire the leaſt to reſemble: and ſo if I writ before in a ſtile that I thought became him, I will now change that into another, which I am ſure becomes my ſelf. In the former, I examined his Arguments for abrogating the <hi>Teſt,</hi> in a ſtrain, which I thought ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what neceſſary for the Informing the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aright, in a matter of ſuch Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that the Preſervation of our <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> is judged to depend upon it, by the Preſumptive <hi>Heir</hi> of the Crown: but now, that I am to argue a point, which requires more of a Gravity, than of an acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of ſtile, I will no more conſider the <hi>Man,</hi> but the <hi>Matter</hi> in hand.</p>
            <p>In a word <q rend="inline">He would perſuade the World, that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is but a Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cety of the Schools, calculated to the <hi>Ariſtotelian</hi> Philoſophy: and not defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned poſitively in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> but that the <hi>Corporal</hi> and <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of the ſubſtance of Chriſts <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> in the Sacrament, was the Doctrine of the Univerſal <hi>Church</hi> in the Primitive Times: and that it is at this day the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received Doctrine by all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Parties in <hi>Europe,</hi> not only the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> and <hi>Lutherans,</hi> but both by the Churches of <hi>Switzerland</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and more particularly by the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> ſo that ſince all that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> means by Tranſubſtantiation is the <hi>Real preſence</hi> and ſince the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> is ſo Univerſally received, it is a heinous thing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133214:2"/>to renounce Tranſubſtantiation; for that is in effect the renouncing the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is the whole ſtrength of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he fortifies by many Cita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to prove that both the Antient-<hi>Fathers</hi> and the Modern <hi>Reformers,</hi> believed the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> and that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believes no more. But to all this I shall offer a few Exceptions.</p>
            <p n="1">I. If <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is only a Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Nicety concerning the <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>Preſence;</hi> where is the hurt of renouncing it? and why are the <hi>Ro. Catholicks</hi> at ſo much pains to have the <hi>Teſt</hi> repealed? for it contains nothing againſt the <hi>Real Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</hi> indeed, if this Argument has any force, it should rather lead the <hi>Ro. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> to take the <hi>Teſt,</hi> ſince according to the Bp they do not renounce in it any Article of Faith, but only a bold curioſity of the Schoolmen. Yet after all, it ſeems they know, that this is contrary to their Doctrine, otherwiſe they would not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo much upon a point of an old and decried Philoſophy.</p>
            <p n="2">II. In order to the ſtating this matter aright, it is neceſſary to give the true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> as it is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the <hi>Reformed.</hi> We all know in what ſenſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> underſtands it, that in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> there is no <hi>Real Bread and Wine,</hi> but that under the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of them we have the true ſubſtance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> glorified <hi>Body.</hi> On the other hand, the <hi>Reformed,</hi> when they found the world generally fond of this phraſe; they by the ſame Spirit of Compliance, which our Saviour and his Apoſtles had for the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that the Primitive Church had (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps to exceſs) for the <hi>Heathens,</hi> retained the phraſe of <hi>Real Preſence:</hi> but as they gave it ſuch a ſenſe as did fully demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that tho they retained a term that had for it a long Preſcription, yet they quite changed its meaning: for they always shewed, that the <hi>Body and blood of Chriſt,</hi> which they believed preſent, was his <hi>Body broken</hi> and his <hi>Blood shed,</hi> that is to ſay, his <hi>Body,</hi> not in its <hi>glorified ſtate,</hi> but as it was <hi>crucified.</hi> So that the preſence belonging to Chriſts <hi>dead Body,</hi> which is not now actually in being, it is only his <hi>Death</hi> that is to be conceived to be preſented to us, and this being the ſenſe that they always give of the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> the <hi>reality</hi> falls only on that conveyance, that is made to us in the Sacrament, by a federal rite of <hi>Chriſts Death</hi> as our <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> The learned Anſwerer to the <hi>Oxford</hi> diſcourſes has ſo fully demonſtrated this from the copious explanations which all the <hi>Reformed</hi> give of that phraſe, that one would think it were not poſſible either to mistake or cavil in ſo clear a point. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> had generally objected to the <hi>Reformers,</hi> that they made the <hi>Sacrament</hi> no more than a bare Commemoratory Feaſt; and ſome few had carried their averſion to that groſs <hi>Preſence</hi> which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had ſet up, to another extream to which the People by a principle of libertiniſm might have been too eaſily carried; if the true Dignity of the Sacrament had not been maintained by expreſſions of great Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty: ſo finding that the world was poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the phraſe of the <hi>real Preſence,</hi> they thought fit to preſerve it, but with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation that was liable to no Ambiguity. Yet it ſeems our <hi>Reformers</hi> in the beginning of Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi>'s Reign had found that the phraſe had more power to carry men to Superſtition, than the explanations gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to it, had to retire them from it, and therefore the Convocation ordered it to be laid aſide, tho that order was ſuppreſſed out of prudence: and the phraſe has been ever ſince in uſe among us, of which Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> has given us a copious account, <hi>Hiſt. Reform.</hi> 2 Vol. 3. Book.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Difference between the notion of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> being a meer Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory Feaſt, and the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> is as great as the value of the Kings head ſtamped upon a Meddal differs from the current coyn, or the Impreſſion made by the Great Seal upon Wax differs from that which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133214:2"/>any carver or graver may make. The one is a meer <hi>Memorial,</hi> but the other has a ſacred badge of Authority in it. The <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb,</hi> was not only a <hi>Remembrance</hi> of the Deliverance of the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but a continuance of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> that <hi>Moſes</hi> made between God and them, which diſtinguished them from all the Nations round about them, as well as the firſt <hi>Paſſeover,</hi> had diſtinguished them from the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> Now it were a ſtrange Inference, becauſe the <hi>Lamb</hi> was called the <hi>Lords Paſſeover,</hi> that is, the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> upon the ſprinkling of whoſe Blood the Angel <hi>paſſed over</hi> or <hi>paſſed</hi> by the Houſes of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when he ſmote the firſt-born of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> to ſay, that there was a change of the ſubſtance of the <hi>Lamb:</hi> or becauſe the Real faith of a Prince is given by his Great Seal, printed on Wax, and affixed to a Parchment, that therefore the ſubſtance of the Wax is changed: ſo it is no leſs abſurd to imagin, that becauſe the Bread and the Wine are ſaid to be the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt</hi> as <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>shed,</hi> that is, his death <hi>Really</hi> and <hi>effectually</hi> offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to us, as our <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> that therfore the ſubſtance of the <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> are chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
            <p>And thus upon the whole matter, that which is preſent in the Sacrament is Chriſt <hi>Dead,</hi> and ſince his death was tranſacted above 1600. years ago, the reality of his preſence, can be no other than a Real offer of his death made to us in an Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and federal ſimbole. I have explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this the more fully, becauſe with this, all the ambiguity in the uſe of that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly received phraſe, falls off.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. As for the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Ancient Church, there has been ſo much ſaid in this <hi>Enquiry,</hi> that a man cannot hope to add any new diſcoveries to what has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready found out: therefore I shall only endeavour to bring ſome of the moſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Obſervations into a narrow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and to ſet them in a good light: and shall firſt offer ſome general <hi>Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> to shew that it is not like, that this was the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Primitive times, and then ſome Poſitive proof of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is no ſlight <hi>Preſumption</hi> againſt it, that we do not find the <hi>Fathers</hi> take any pains to anſwer the Objections that do naturally ariſe out of the preſent Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> theſe Objections do not ariſe out of profound ſtudy, or great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but from the plain dictates of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, which make it hard (to ſay no more) for us to believe, <hi>that a Body can be in more places than one at once, and that it can be in a place after the manner of a ſpirit: that Accidents can be without their ſubject; or that our ſenſes can deceive us in the plaineſt caſes:</hi> we find the <hi>Fathers</hi> explain ſome abſtruſe difficulties that ariſe out of other Myſteries, that were leſs known, and were more Speculative: and while they are thought perhaps to over-do the one, it is a little ſtrange that they should never touch the other: but on the contrary, when they treat of Philoſophical matters, they expreſs themſelves roundly in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to thoſe conſequences of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: whereas ſince this Doctrine has been received, we ſee all the ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Philoſophy, have been ſo mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as to keep a reſerve for this Doctrine. So that the uncautious way in which the Fathers handled them (in proof of which Volumes of quotations can be made) shews they had not then received that <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which muſt of neceſſity give them occaſion to write otherwiſe than they did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We find the <hi>Heathens</hi> ſtudied to load the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> with all the heavieſt Imputations that they could give it. They objected to them the believing a God that was born, and that dyed, and the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead, and many leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which ſeemed abſurd to them: they had malice enough to ſeek out every thing that could diſgrace a <hi>Religion</hi> which grew too hard for them: but they never once object this, of <hi>making a God out of a piece of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133214:3"/>Bread, and then eating him:</hi> if this had been the Doctrine of thoſe Ages, the <hi>Heathens,</hi> chiefly <hi>Celſus,</hi> and <hi>Porphiry,</hi> but above all <hi>Julian,</hi> could not have been Ignorant of it. Now it does not ſtand with common ſenſe to think, that thoſe who inſiſt much upon Inconſiderable things, could have paſſed over this, which is both ſo ſenſible and of ſuch Importance, if it had been the received belief of thoſe Ages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is alſo of weight, that there were no diſputes nor Hereſies upon this point during the firſt Ages; and that none of the <hi>Hereticks</hi> ever objected it to the <hi>Doctors</hi> of the Church. We find they contended about all other Points: now this has ſo many difficulties in it, that it should ſeem a little ſtrange, that all mens underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings should have been then ſo eaſy and conſenting, that this was the ſingle point of the whole Body of Divinity, about which the Church had no diſpute for the firſt <hi>Seven</hi> Centuries. It therfore inclines a man rather to think, that becauſe there was no diſputes concerning it, therefore it was not then broached: ſince we ſee plainly, that ever ſince it was broached in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> it has occaſioned laſting Diſputes, both with thoſe who could not be brought to believe it, and with one another concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſeveral ways of explaining and maintaining it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is alſo a ſtrong <hi>Prejudice</hi> againſt the Antiquity of this Doctrine, that there were none of thoſe rites in the firſt ages which have crept in in the latter: which were ſuch natural conſequences of it, that the belief of the one making way for the other, we may conclude, that where the one were not practiſed, the other was not believed. I will not mention all the Pomp which the latter Ages have Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to raiſe the luſtre of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> with which the former Ages were unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted. It is enough to obſerve, that the <hi>Adoration</hi> of the Sacrament, was ſuch a neceſſary Conſequence of this <hi>Doctrine,</hi> that ſince the Primitive Times know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it, as the <hi>Greek</hi> Church does not to this day, it is perhaps more than a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,</hi> that they believed it not.</p>
            <p n="5">V. But now I come to more Poſitive and convincing proofs: and</p>
            <p n="1">1. The language of the whole Church, is only to be found in the <hi>Liturgies</hi> which are more ſeverely compoſed than Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Diſcourſes; and of all the parts of the Office, the <hi>Prayer of Conſecration,</hi> is that in which we muſt hope to find moſt certainly the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church: we find then in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Century,</hi> that in the Prayer of Conſecration the <hi>Elements</hi> were ſaid to be the <hi>Types of the Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſil</hi> Informs us from the <hi>Greek Liturgies;</hi> and <hi>the Figure of his Body and Blood,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Informs us, from the <hi>Latine Liturgies:</hi> The <hi>Prayer</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration,</hi> that is now in the <hi>Canon</hi> of the <hi>Maſs,</hi> is in a great part the ſame with that which is cited by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> but with this Important difference, that inſtead of the words, <hi>which is the Figure of the Body and Blood of Chriſt</hi> that are in the former, there is a petition added in the latter, that <hi>the gifts may be to us the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> If we had ſo many of the Mſs. of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Liturgies</hi> left, as to be able to find out the time in which the <hi>Prayer</hi> of Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration was altered, from what it was in S. <hi>Ambroſes</hi> days, to what it is now, this would be no ſmall Article in the <hi>Hiſtory of Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> but moſt of theſe are loſt; ſince then the Antient Church could not believe otherwiſe of the Sacrament, than as she expreſſed her ſelf concerning it, in the <hi>Prayer of Conſecration;</hi> It is plain, that her firſt <hi>Doctrine</hi> concerning it, was, that the <hi>Bread and Wine were the Types and the Figure of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſecond proof is from the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy, that was began by the <hi>Apollinariſts,</hi> and carried on by the <hi>Eutichians,</hi> whether Chriſts humanity was ſwallowed up of his Divinity or not? The <hi>Eutichians</hi> made uſe of the General Expreſſions, by which the change in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> ſeemed to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133214:3"/>carried ſo far, that the Bread and Wine were ſwallowed up by it; and from this they inferred, that in like manner the human nature of Chriſt was ſwallowed up by his Divinity: but in oppoſition to all this, we find <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople, Ephrem</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, Gelaſius</hi> the Pope, <hi>Theodoret</hi> a Bp in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſer, and <hi>Facundus</hi> a Bp in <hi>Affrick,</hi> all within the compaſs of little more than an Age, agree almoſt in the ſame words, in refuting all this: aſſerting, <hi>that as the human nature in Chriſt remained ſtill the ſame that it was before, notwithſtanding its union with his divine Nature, even ſo the Bread and Wine retained ſtill their former</hi> Nature, Subſtance and Form, and that <hi>they are only ſanctified, not by the change of their</hi> Nature, <hi>but by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Grace to Nature.</hi> This they do in terms plain, and beyond all exception; and <hi>Theodoret</hi> goes over the matter again and again, in two different Treatiſes, ſo that no matter of fact can appear more plainly, then that the whole Church <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> did in the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Centuries</hi> believe that the Sanctification of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in the Sacrament, did no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their natures, than the union of the two natures in Chriſt, did deſtroy his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature.</p>
            <p>A 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> proof is taken from a practice which I will not offer to juſtify, how Antient ſoever it may have been: It appears in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in the Antienteſt <hi>Liturgies</hi> now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; and is a <hi>Prayer</hi> in which the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is ſaid to be offered up in <hi>honour of the Saint of the day,</hi> to which a petition is added, that it may be <hi>accepted of God by the Interceſſion of the Saint.</hi> This is yet in the <hi>Miſſal,</hi> and is uſed upon moſt of the Saints days: now if the Sacrament was then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be the <hi>very Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> there is nothing more <hi>crude,</hi> not to ſay <hi>prophane,</hi> to offer this up to the <hi>honour of a Saint,</hi> and to pray that the Sacrifice of Chriſts body may be accepted of God thro the Interceſſion of a <hi>Saint.</hi> Therefore to give any tollerable ſenſe to theſe words, we muſt conclude, that tho theſe Prayers have been continued in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ſince this Opinion prevailed, yet they were never made in an Age in which it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. The only meaning that can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to theſe words, is, that they made the <hi>Saints days,</hi> days of Communion, as well as the <hi>Sundays</hi> were: and upon that they prayed that the Sacrament which they received that day, to do the more honour to the Memory of the Saint, might be recommended to the divine Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance by the Interceſſion of the Saint: ſo that this Superſtitious practice, shews plainly, that the <hi>Church</hi> had not, even when it began, received the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the change of the Elements into the Body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>I will not purſue the proof of this point further, nor will I enter into a particular recital of the Sayings of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> upon this ſubject; which would carry me far: and it is done ſo copiouſly by others, that I had rather refer my Reader to them, than offer him a lean abridgment of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <p>I shall only add, that the <hi>Preſumptions</hi> and Proofs that I have offered are much more to be valued, than the pious and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torical Figures by which many of the <hi>Fathers</hi> have ſet forth the manner of Chriſts <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> in the Sacrament. One thing is plain, that in moſt of them, they repreſent Chriſt preſent in his dead and crucified ſtate, which appears moſt eminently in S. <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> ſo that this aggreed with that notion of a <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> that was formerly explained. Men that have at the ſame time, all the heat in their Imaginations that Eloquence can raiſe, and all the fervour in their heart which devotion can inſpire, are ſeldom ſo correct in their phraſes and figures, as not to need ſome allowances: therfore one plain proof of their Opinions from their reaſonings when in cold blood, ought to be of much more weight than all their Tranſports and Amplificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:133214:4"/>
            <p>From this General view of the State of the <hi>Church</hi> during the firſt <hi>Centuries,</hi> I come next to conſider the ſteps of the change which was afterwards made. I will not offer to trace out that Hiſtory, which Mr. <hi>Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogue</hi> has done Copiouſly, whom I the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mention becauſe he is put in <hi>English.</hi> I shall only obſerve, that by reaſon of the high expreſſions which were uſed upon the occaſion of the <hi>Eutichean</hi> Controverſy, formerly mentioned, by which the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of the <hi>Elements</hi> was compared to the Union of the humane nature of Chriſt with his Divinity, a great ſtep was made to all that followed: during the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute concerning <hi>Images,</hi> thoſe who oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the worship of them ſaid, according to all the Antient Liturgies, that they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed acknowledged one <hi>Image</hi> of Chriſt, which was the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> thoſe who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted that piece of ſuperſtition (for I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the calling it <hi>Idolatry</hi> to its proper place) had the Impudence to deny that it had ever been called the <hi>Image of Chriſts Body and Blood:</hi> and ſaid, that it was really his <hi>Body and Blood.</hi> We will not much Diſpute concerning an Age, in which the World ſeemed mad with a zeal for the Worship of <hi>Images;</hi> and in which <hi>Rebellion</hi> and the depoſing of <hi>Princes</hi> upon the pretence of Hereſy, began to be put in practiſe: ſuch times as theſe, we willingly yield up to our Adverſaries. Yet <hi>Damaſcene,</hi> and the <hi>Greek</hi> Church after him, carried this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no further than to aſſert an Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Elements,</hi> into an union with the <hi>Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> But when the Monk of <hi>Corbie</hi> began to carry the matter yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to ſay, that the <hi>Elements</hi> were changed into the <hi>very Body of Chriſt that was born of the Virgin,</hi> we find all the great men of that Age, both in <hi>France, Germany,</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> writ againſt him: and he himſelf owns that he was looked upon as an Innovator; Thoſe who writ againſt him, chiefly <hi>Rabanus Maurus,</hi> and <hi>Bertram</hi> or <hi>Ratramne,</hi> did ſo plainly aſſert the Ancient opinion of the Sacraments being the <hi>Figure of the Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs our ſelves more formally than they did: and from thence it was that our <hi>Saxon</hi> Homily on <hi>Eaſter</hi> Day was ſo expreſs in this point. Yet the War and the <hi>Northern</hi> Invaſions that followed, put the World into ſo much diſorder, that all Diſputes were ſoon forgot, and that in the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury,</hi> this Opinion which had ſo many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſans in the <hi>ninth,</hi> was generally decried and much abandoned.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. But with relation to thoſe Ages in which it was received, ſome obſervations occur ſo readily, to every one that knows Hiſtory, that it is only for the ſake of the more Ignorant, that I make them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They were times of ſo much Ignorance, that it is ſcarce conceivable to any but to thoſe who have laboured a little in reading the productions of thoſe Ages; which is the drieſt piece of ſtudy I know: the ſtile in which they writ, and their way of arguing, and explaining ſcripture, are all of a piece, both matter and form are equally barbarous. Now in ſuch times, as the Ignorant populace were eaſily miſled, ſo there is ſome what in Incredible ſtories and Opinions, that makes them paſs as eaſily, as men are apt to fancy they ſee Sprights in the Night: nay the more of Myſtery and Darkneſs that there is in any Opinion, ſuch times are apt to cherish it the more for that very reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe were ages in which the whole Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Order</hi> had entred into ſuch Conſpiracies againſt the <hi>State,</hi> which were managed and ſet on by ſuch vigour by the <hi>Popes,</hi> that every Opinion which tended to render the perſons of Church men <hi>Sacred,</hi> and to raiſe their Character, was likely to receive the beſt entertainment, and the greateſt encouragment poſſible. Nothing could ſo ſecure the perſons of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and render them ſo conſiderable, as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>that they made their God:</hi> and in ſuch Ages no Armour was of ſo ſure a proof as for a Prieſt to take his God in his hands.</p>
            <p>Now it is known, that as P. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, who condemned <hi>Berengarius,</hi> laid
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133214:4"/>the foundations of the Eccleſiaſtical Empire, by eſtablishing the Depoſing power, ſo P. <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> who got <hi>Transſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be decreed in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Council of the <hi>Lateran,</hi> ſeemed to have compleated the project; by the Addition made to the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing power, of transferring the Dominions of the Depoſed <hi>Prince</hi> to whom he pleaſed. Since before this, the Dominions muſt have gone to the next Heirs of the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Prince. It is then ſo plain, that the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Tranſubſtantiation, was ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the advancing of thoſe ends, that it had been a wonder indeed, if it being once ſet on foot, it had not been eſtablished in ſuch times.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thoſe Ages were ſo corrupt, and more particularly the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and chiefly the <hi>Popes,</hi> were by the Confeſſion of all writers ſo exceſſively vicious, that ſuch men could have no regard to truth in any of their Deciſions. Intereſt muſt have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried all other things before it, with ſuch <hi>Popes,</hi> who according to the Hiſtorians of their own Communion, were perhaps the worſt men that ever lived. Their Vices were ſo crying, that nothing but the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that is due to Writers of their own time, and their own Church, could determine us to believe them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As the Ignorance and Vices of thoſe times derogate juſtly from all the credit that is due to them, ſo the Cruelty which followed their Deciſions, and which was Imployed in the Execution of them, makes it appear rather a ſtranger thing that ſo many oppoſed them, then that ſo many ſubmitted to them. When <hi>Inquiſitors</hi> or <hi>Dragoons</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage an Argument, how <hi>ſtrong ſoever the Spirit</hi> may be, in oppoſing it, it is certain the <hi>Flesh will be weak,</hi> and will ply eaſily. When <hi>Princes</hi> were threatned with Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and <hi>Hereticks</hi> with Extirpation, and when both were executed with ſo much rigour, the ſucceſs of all the Doctrines that were eſtablished in thoſe days, ought to make no Impreſſion on us, in its favour.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. It is no leſs plain that there was a great and vigorous oppoſition made to every ſtep of the progreſs of this Doctrine. When the <hi>Eutichi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> firſt made uſe of it, the greateſt men of that Age ſet themſelves againſt it. When the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shippers of <hi>Images</hi> did afterwards deny that the <hi>Sacrament</hi> was the <hi>Image of the Body and Blood of Chriſt,</hi> a General <hi>Council</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> aſſerted, according to the Antient <hi>Liturgies,</hi> the Contrary <hi>Propoſition.</hi> When <hi>Paſchaſe Radbert</hi> ſet on Foot the <hi>Corporal Preſence,</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> all the great men of the Age writ againſt him. <hi>Berenger</hi> was likewiſe highly eſteemed, and had many ſecret Followers, when this Doctrine was firſt decreed: and ever ſince the time of the <hi>Council</hi> of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> that Tranſubſtantiation was eſtablished, there have been whole bodies of men that have oppoſed it, and that have fallen as Sacrifices to the Rages of the Inquiſitors. And by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of thoſe of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> of which I have ſeen the Original <hi>Records,</hi> for the ſpace of twenty years, it appears that as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was the Article upon which they were always chiefly examined, ſo it was that which many of them did the moſt conſtantly deny, ſo far were they on both ſides from looking on it only as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of the <hi>Real Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The Novelty of this <hi>Doctrine</hi> appears plainly by the ſtrange work that the <hi>Schools</hi> have made with it, ſince they got it among them, both in their Philoſophy and Divinity, and by the many different methods that they took for explaining it, till they had licked it into the shape, in which it is now: which is as plain an Evidence of the Novelty of the Doctrine as can be imagined. The learned Mr. <hi>Alix</hi> has given us a clear Deduction of all that confuſion, into which it has caſt the <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and the many various Methods that they fell on for maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> they thought the body of Chriſt was broken by the Teeth of the Faithful: then that appearing abſurd, and ſubjecting our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to new ſufferings; the Doctrine of a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies being in a place after the manner of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was ſet up. And as to the change, ſome thought, that the Matter of Bread remained, but that it was united to the Body of Chriſt, as nourishment is digeſted into our Bodies: others thought, that the <hi>Form</hi> of Bread remained, the <hi>Matter</hi> only being changed: and ſome thought, that the <hi>Bread</hi> was only with-drawn to give place to the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt, whereas others thought it was Annihilated. While the better Judges had always an eye either to a <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> or to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133214:5"/>ſuch an Aſſumption of the Bread and Wine by the Eternal Word, as made the Sacrament in ſome ſenſe his <hi>Body</hi> indeed; but not that Body which is now in Heaven. All theſe different Opinions, in which the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> were divided, even after the Deciſion made by Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> in the Council of the <hi>Lateran,</hi> shew, that the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> being a Novelty, men did not yet know how to mould or form it: but in proceſs of time the whole Philoſophy was ſo digeſted, as to prepare all <hi>Schollars</hi> in their firſt formation to receive it the more eaſily. And in our Age, in which that Philoſophy has loſt its credit, what pains do they take to ſuppreſs the <hi>New</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, as ſeeing that it cannot be ſo eaſily ſubdued to ſupport this Doctrine as the <hi>Old</hi> one was. And it is no unpleaſant thing to ſee the Shifts to which the Partiſans of the <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy are driven, to explain themſelves: which are indeed ſo very ridiculous, that one can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly think that thoſe who make uſe of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them: for they are plainly rather Tricks and Excuſes than Anſwers.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. No man can deny, that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but he that will diſpute the Authority of the Councils of the <hi>Lateran</hi> and <hi>Trent:</hi> now tho ſome have done the firſt avowedly, yet as their number is ſmall, and their Opinion decried, ſo for the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> tho I have known ſome of that Communion, who do not look upon it as a <hi>General Council,</hi> and tho it is not at all received in <hi>France,</hi> neither as to Doctrine nor Diſcipline, yet the contrary opinion is ſo univerſally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that they who think otherwiſe, dare not ſpeak out: and ſo give their Opinion as a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, which they truſt in confidence, rather than as a Doctrine which they will own. But ſetting aſide the Authority of theſe <hi>Councils,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Reſolution of Faith in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> being <hi>Tradition,</hi> it cannot be denied, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and general Tradition in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> theſe laſt 500. <hi>years,</hi> has been in favour of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and that is witneſſed by all the Evidences by which it is poſſible to know <hi>Tradition.</hi> The Writings of Learned Men, the Sermons of Preachers, the Proceedings of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunals, the Deciſions of Councils, that if they were not <hi>general,</hi> were yet very numerous, and above all by the many Authentical Declarations that <hi>Popes</hi> have made in this matter. So that either <hi>Tradition</hi> is to be forever rejected as a falſe conveyance, or this is the received <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from which She can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver depart, without giving up both her <hi>Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and the Authority of <hi>Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">X. There is not any one point, in which all the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> do more unanimouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, than in the rejecting of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> as appears both by the Harmony of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and by the current of all the Reformed Writers. And for the <hi>Real Preſence,</hi> tho the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> explain it by a <hi>Conſubſtantiation,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Reformed,</hi> by a Reality of Vertue and Efficacy, and a Preſence of Chriſt as cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, yet all of them have taken much pains to shew, that in what ſenſe ſoever they meant it, they were ſtill far enough from <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This demonſtrates the Wiſdom of our <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators,</hi> in ſingling out this to be the ſole point of the <hi>Teſt</hi> for Imployments: ſince it is perhaps the only point in Controverſy, in which the whole Church of <hi>Rome</hi> holds the Affirmative, and the whole <hi>Reformed</hi> hold the Negative. And it is as certain, that <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the Church of <hi>England;</hi> it being by name condemned in our <hi>Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus I hope the whole <hi>Plea</hi> of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in favour of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, in all its three Branches: which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to the Doctrine of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as well as of the other <hi>Reformed</hi> Churches. I have not loaded this Paper with Quotations: becauſe I intended to be short: but I am ready to make good all the matters of fact aſſerted in it, under the higheſt pains of Infamy if I fail in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: and beſides, the more Voluminous Works that have been writ on this ſubject, ſuch as <hi>Albertines, Claud</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Arnaud,</hi> and F. <hi>Nonet, Larrogues</hi> Hiſtory of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> there have been ſo many learned Diſcourſes written of late on this Subject, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar two Anſwers to the Bishops <hi>Book,</hi> that if it had not been thought expedient that I should have caſt the whole matter into a short Paper, I should not have judged it neceſſary to trouble the world with more Diſcourſes on a ſubject that ſeems exhauſted. I will add no more, but that by the next I will give another Paper of the ſame Bulk upon the <hi>Idolatry of the Church of</hi> Rome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
